字幕來源：CMCT
■
后期：阿小小海
片名  2001太空漫游
先生到了  請上主甲板
Here you are, sir. Main level, please.
好的  回程時再見
Right. See you on the way back.
-再見  -再見
-Bye. -Bye.
先生  早安  -早安
-Good morning, sir. -Morning.
你已經有好久沒到這兒來了  -很高興再見到你
-We haven't seen you for a long time. -Nice to see you again.
這次飛行愉快嗎  -很好  謝謝
-Did you have a pleasant flight? -Very nice.
我想基地室的米勒先生  應該在等我
Mr. Miller of Station Security is supposed to meet me.
-我幫你叫他好嗎  -麻煩你  他來了
-May I call him for you? -Would you? Here he is!
博士你好  抱歉我遲到了
-Hello, Dr. Floyd. -Hello, Miller.
沒關系  你看來氣色不錯
-Sorry I'm late. -That's all right.
謝謝  真高興你回來
It's nice to have you back.
這次旅途愉快嗎  -很好
-Did you have a good flight? -Very nice.
-那就好  我們進去好嗎  -請使用17號門
-Shall we go through? -Would you please use number 17?
謝謝你  透納小姐
Thank you, Miss Turner.
請走這邊
This way.
歡迎接受聲影測試
Welcome to Voice Print Identification.
當你看見紅燈亮時
When you see the red light go on,
請按順序說出
please state in the following order:
你的目的地  國籍  還有你的全名
Your destination, your nationality and your full name.
先說姓  然后是名字和縮寫
Surname first, Christian name, and initial.
月球、美國籍  佛洛伊德·赫伍德·R
Moon. American. Floyd, Heywood R.
謝謝  你已通過聲影測試
Thank you. You are cleared through Voice Print Identification.
謝謝
Thank you.
-我有空吃早餐嗎  -也許可以
-Have I got time for breakfast? -I think we can manage that.
我還有多久出發
How long have I got?
大概一小時十分鐘
Your flight leaves in an hour and 10 minutes.
事實上  我已替你訂了位
I've reserved a table for you in the Earthlight Room.
上次你來是七  八個月前吧
It's been 7 or 8 months since you were here, hasn't it?
我想想看  是去年六月  對  有八個月了
Let's see. Yeah, about 8 months.
我想你已看過新單位的工作
I suppose you saw the work on the new section?
是很不錯的嗎  -不錯
-Coming along great, huh? -Yeah, it's fine.
等一等
Oh, wait!
我想打通電話  你先到餐廳  我去找你
I've got to make a couple calls. I'll meet you in the restaurant.
-哈嘍  -嗯
-Hello. -Yes.
-哈羅  寶貝  -嗯
-Hiya, squirt! -All right.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
我在玩
Playing.
媽媽呢
Where's Mummy?
上街買東西
Gone to shopping.
-那誰照顧你  -瑞契兒
-Who's taking care of you? -Rachel.
我跟她講話好嗎  -她去洗手間了
-May I speak to Rachel, please? -She's gone to the bathroom.
明天你能來參加我的派對嗎
Are you coming to my party tomorrow?
抱歉  甜心  我不能去
I'm sorry, sweetheart, but I can't.
為什么
Why not?
你知道  爸爸正在旅行
Well, you know, Daddy's traveling.
很抱歉  我真的不能去
Very sorry about it, but I just can't.
可是我可以送你一個禮物
I'm going to send you a very nice present, though.
好吧
All right.
你想要什么特別的東西嗎有的
-Anything special that you want? -Yes.
什么東西
What?
電話
A telephone.
我們已經通有很多電話了
We've got lots of telephones already.
你能不能想想其它的東西
Can't you think of anything else for your birthday?
來慶祝你的生日
Something special?
-有啊  -什么東西
-Yes. -What?
一只猩猩
A bush baby.
一只猩猩  那我們得想想辦法找找看
A bush baby? We'll have to see about that.
甜心  我要你轉告媽咪  你要記得
I want you to tell Mummy something for me. Will you remember?
我會
Yeah.
你告訴媽咪我打過電話  好嗎
Tell Mummy that I telephoned. Okay?
告訴她  明天我會再打電話  好嗎
And that I'll try to telephone again tomorrow.
你會告訴她吧
Now, will you tell her that?
-我會的  -很好  甜心  明天生日好好玩
-Yeah. -Okay, sweetheart. Have a nice birthday tomorrow.
好
All right.
明天生日派對愉快
And have a nice birthday party tomorrow too, huh?
好
All right.
好了  要小心  要乖乖  好嗎
Take care and be a good girl, won't you?
-好的  -再見
All right. Bye-bye!
再見  生日快樂
Bye-bye! Happy birthday!
電話費$1.70
(俄語)
艾琳娜  真高興見到你
Elena, how nice to see you again.
赫伍德  真高興在此見到你
Heywood, what a wonderful surprise!
-你看起來很不錯  -謝謝  你看起來也很不錯
-You're looking wonderful. -You're looking well too.
這是我的好朋友  佛博士
This is my friend, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
我來介紹一下  卡莉娜博士
I'd like you to meet Dr. Kalinan.
你好  史博士  你好
Dr. Stretyneva.
這位是史麥斯洛夫博士
And this is Dr. Andrei Smyslov.
你好  久仰大名
How do you do? I've heard a lot about you.
請坐
Do sit down.
-我們  -不用客氣  請
-Well, we-- -No, no, please.
謝謝
Thank you.
-博士要喝點什么不用  -謝謝你
-Would you like a drink, Doctor? -No, thank you.
其實我還沒吃早餐呢  我約了人在餐廳見面
I haven't had breakfast yet. Someone's meeting me in the restaurant.
如果各位不介意  我坐幾分鐘就走
I'll just sit with you a moment. Then I'll be off.
-真的不喝點什么嗎  -不客氣  謝謝你
-Are you quite sure? -Quite sure, thank you.
-葛雷哥近來如何  -他很好
-Well, how's Gregor? -He's fine.
他在波羅的海從事海底實驗
He's been doing underwater research in the Baltic...
所以最近我們很少碰面
...so I'm afraid we don't see very much of each other these days.
-如果見到他  記著代我問好  -當然
-When you see him, give him my regards. -Yes, of course.
你們大伙要去那里  上還是下
Well, where are you all off to? Up or down?
我們正準備回家
We're going home.
我們剛花了三個月的時間  校正柴林科號上的新天線
We've just spent 3 months calibrating the new antenna at Tchalinko.
-你呢  -我正要去克萊威斯
-What about you? -I'm on my way to Clavius.
噢  是嗎
Oh, are you?
克萊威斯
Clavius.
博士  請不要介意我太好奇
Dr. Floyd, I hope you don't think I'm being too inquisitive...
但是也許你可以澄清一下
...but perhaps you can clear up the big mystery
到底那里發生了什么事
about what is going on there.
我恐怕不太了解你的意思
I'm afraid I don't know what you mean.
過去兩個星期  克萊威斯發生怪事
For the past two weeks...
...some extremely odd things have been happening at Clavius.
-真的嗎  -真的
-Oh, really? -Yes, yes.
例如  當你打電話到該基地時
For one thing, when you phone the base,
只能聽到電話錄音
all you get is a recording...
重覆的告訴你線路故障
...which repeats that the phone lines are temporarily out of order.
可能是他們的裝備故障
Probably having some trouble with their equipment.
是的  起先我們也是這么想
That's what we thought at first,
但是到現在為止已經十天了
but it's been going on now for 10 days.
你是說在過去十天中  你們無法與任何人聯絡
You haven't been able to contact anyone for 10 days?
正是如此
That's right.
原來如此
Oh, I see.
還有一件事  兩天前我們有一輛火箭巴士
There's another thing. Two days ago, one of our rocket buses...
被拒絕在克萊威斯緊急迫降
...was denied permission for an emergency landing.
那就真的有些奇怪了
That does sound odd.
是的  恐怕這件事將會引起爭執
I'm afraid there's going to be a bit of a row about it.
拒絕迫降是違反  國際航空暨太空協定
Denying the men permission to land violates the IAS Convention.
是的  那當然  機員們都平安歸來了嗎
Yes, of course. Did the crew get back all right?
是的  是的  很慶幸
Fortunately, they did.
是的  很高興聽到這樣
Well, I'm glad about that.
佛博士對你不愿討論的問題
At the risk of pressing you on
一再追問  也許有些冒犯
a point you seem reticent to discuss...
但是我可不可以  直接的問你一個問題
...may I ask you a straightforward question?
當然可以
Well, certainly.
坦白說  我們有可靠的情報指出
Frankly, we have had some very reliable intelligence reports that...
在克萊威斯發生一種  不明來源  十分嚴重的傳染病
...quite a serious epidemic has broken out at Clavius.
Something, apparently, of an unknown origin.
這應該就是事情的真相吧
Is this, in fact, what has happened?
很抱歉  史麥斯博士
I'm sorry, Dr. Smyslov, but...
我無法與你討論這件事
...I'm really not at liberty to discuss this.
這點我了解
I understand.
但是這個傳染病可能  很容易就傳染到我們的基地
But this epidemic could easily spread to our base.
我們必須要知道事情的真相
We should be given all the facts.
我知道
Yes, I know.
不過我已說過  我無法討論這個問題
As I said, I'm not at liberty to discuss it.
你確定不改變主意來一杯嗎
Won't you change your mind about that drink?
確定  現在我真的必須走了
No, I'm positive. I really must be going.
希望你和你太太能一起參加  六月舉行的國際航空會議
I hope you and your wife come to the IAC Conference.
我們會想辦法  希望屆時能前來參加
I hope we can make it.
假如你們能來  記得寶貝女兒一起帶來
If you do, bring that darling little daughter with you.
那要看學校假期而定
That'll depend on school vacations and all that sort of thing.
如果可以  一定帶來
If we can, we will.
不要忘記不論何時  到美國來一定要來找我
You've got an invitation if you ever get to the States.
當然  葛雷哥和我  都期待著去看你們
Gregor and I will look forward to seeing you.
好了  艾琳娜  再見
Goodbye, Elena.
很榮幸見到你們  史麥斯洛夫博士
It's been a pleasure meeting you all. Dr. Smyslov.
佛博士  不管你是什么理由
Whatever the reasons for your visit,
去克萊威斯  祝你幸運
the very best of luck to you.
謝謝你們
Thank you.
各位女士
Ladies.
(俄語)
零重力廁所  乘客使用前應先閱讀說明
對不起  赫伍森博士  我拍完了
Excuse me, Dr. Halvorsen. I'm through now.
-謝謝各位  -不客氣
-Thank you very much, gentlemen. -You're welcome.
我知道  大家和我一樣都非常高興
Well...
...I know you will all want to join with me...
歡迎我們杰出的朋友和同事
...in welcoming our distinguished friend and colleague...
來自國家太空航行委員會  赫伍德  佛洛伊德博士
...from the National Council of Astronautics, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
佛博士今天特別來到  克萊威斯參加我們的工作
Dr. Floyd has come up specially to Clavius to be with us today.
在簡報前  我想他一定很樂意說幾句話
Before the briefing, he'd like to have a few words with you.
佛博士
Dr. Floyd?
謝謝赫伍森博士
Thank you, Dr. Halvorsen.
大家好  很高興回來和大家在一起
Hi, everybody. Nice to be back with you.
首先我帶來豪爾博士的口信
First, I bring a personal message from Dr. Howell...
他對各位所作的犧牲  表示由衷的感激
...who has asked me to convey his deep appreciation...
...for the many sacrifices you've had to make.
同時他對各位在科學史上
And, of course,
最有意義的發現  表示祝賀
his congratulations on your discovery...
同時他對各位在科學史上
...which may prove to be among the most significant
最有意義的發現  表示祝賀
in the history of science.
現在.  .
Now...
我知道關于這件事是否保密  你們曾有不同的看法
...I know there have been some conflicting views...
...regarding the need for complete security in this matter.
說得更明白點
More specifically,
基地上有傳染病的傳說  就是這樣產生的
your opposition to the cover story...
說得更明白點
...created to give the impression of
基地上有傳染病的傳說  就是這樣產生的
an epidemic at the base.
我了解這和原則有所違背
I understand that beyond it being a matter of principle...
你們大家都深受其困擾
...many of you are troubled by the concern and anxiety...
擔心傳染病的謠言
...this story of an epidemic might
會使地球上的親友感到焦慮
cause to your relatives and friends on Earth.
我完全同情持反對意見者
I completely sympathize with your negative views.
我自己也深受謠言困擾
I find this cover story personally embarrassing, myself.
然而  我仍堅持要絕對保密
However, I accept the need for absolute secrecy in this.
我希望你們也同樣贊成
And I hope you will too.
我相信大家都很清楚
I'm sure you're all aware of the grave potential...
如果在沒適當準備下公布此事
...for cultural shock and social disorientation...
...contained in this situation...
對文化的沖激及  社會產生迷惑的可能性
...if the facts were prematurely made public...
...without adequate preparation and conditioning.
無論如何
Anyway...
這是委員會的意思
...this is the view of the Council.
我來此的目的  正是搜集事實與意見
The purpose of my visit is to gather additional facts and opinions...
以便草擬報告向委員會建議  何時及如何公布這件事情
...on the situation...
...and to prepare a report to the Council...
以便草擬報告向委員會建議
...recommending when and how
何時及如何公布這件事情
the news should eventually be announced.
如果哪位提供我意見和看法  如果你愿意私底下也可以
If any of you would like to give me your views and opinions...
我將很高興將它寫進報告
...in private, if you like, I will be happy to include them in my report.
好了  我想這件事到此為止  有無問題
Well, I think that's about it.
有無問題
Any questions?
佛博士  這件事究竟要保密多久
Dr. Floyd, have you any idea how much longer...
...this cover story will have to be maintained?
我不知道  比爾
I don't know, Bill.
我想保密時間的長短  需由委員會視狀況而定
I suppose for as long as deemed necessary by the Council.
當然  在決定公布前  要有足夠的時間做全盤研究
There must be adequate time for a full study...
...before any thought can be given to making a public announcement.
對了  你們當中有人已知道  委員會已正式要求
As some of you know, the Council has requested...
任何知道此事的人  都必須保密
...that security oaths be obtained in writing...
...from everyone who has knowledge of this event.
還有問題嗎
Were there any more questions?
我確定我們大家都想
I'm sure we all want to cooperate with Dr.
盡可能和佛博士合作
Floyd as fully as possible...
似乎沒什么問題了
...and as there are no more questions,
我想接下來應該開始簡報
we ought to get on with the briefing.
-謝謝你佛博士  -謝謝
-Thank you, Dr. Floyd. -Thank you.
有人餓了嗎
Anybody hungry?
-有什么好吃的  -你們說呢
-What've we got? -You name it.
-這是什么雞肉嗎  -類似雞的東西
-Is this chicken? -Something like that.
不管怎么樣  嘗嘗看
Tastes the same, anyway.
有火腿嗎
Got any ham?
火腿  火腿  火腿
Ham, ham, ham....
有  在這
There, that's it.
看起來不錯
Look pretty good.
他們隨時都在改進
They're getting better at it all the time.
-你的演講非常棒  赫伍德  -的確如此
-That was an excellent speech. -It certainly was.
我相信他能提高全體的士氣
I'm sure it beefed up morale a lot.
謝謝你  雷夫
Thanks, Ralph.
我認為你們也表現的非常好
By the way, you've both done a wonderful job.
我很欣賞你們處理的方法
I admire how you've handled this.
這樣做是我們的職責
It's our job to do this thing the way you want it done.
很高興能達到這個要求
We're only too happy to be able to oblige.
你看過這些嗎
Have you seen these yet?
整個事件就是從這里開始
-Have a look. -Here's what started the whole thing.
噢耶
Oh, yeah.
當初我們發現它時  以為是個磁性巖石的外殼
When we found it, we thought it might be magnetic rock...
但是所有地質學上的  檢驗都與此相反
...but all the geological evidence was against it.
甚至沒有一個如此
And not even a nickel-iron meteorite
巨大的鎳鐵隕石能產生  這樣強烈的磁場
could produce a field this intense.
所以我們決定去看看
So we decided to have a look.
我們認為是某種  被埋葬建筑物較上層部份
We thought it was part of a buried structure...
所以把四周挖掘開  很不幸沒有任何的發現
...so we excavated out, but we didn't find anything else.
所有的證據似乎完全確定
And the evidence seems pretty conclusive that...
它不是被自然的侵蝕或其它力量所掩蓋
...it hasn't been covered by erosion or other forces.
它似乎是經過謹慎埋葬的
It's been deliberately buried.
謹慎的埋葬
Deliberately buried.
來點咖啡如何
How about a little coffee?
-太棒了  -好主意
-Great. -Good idea.
我想你們也猜不出那是什么
I don't suppose you have any idea what the damn thing is?
我希望我們知道
I wish to hell we did.
唯一可以確定的是  那是四百萬年前所埋的
The only thing we're sure of is it was buried 4 million years ago.
我應該說  你們確實是有重大的發現
Well, I must say, you guys have certainly come up with something.
看著點  很燙
Watch this, now. It's hot.
木星任務18個月后
晚安
Good evening.
三星期前  美國太空船發現者一號
Three weeks ago, the American spacecraft Discovery One...
開始全程五億里的木星航行
...left on its half-billion mile voyage to Jupiter.
寫下人類首次  到達這遙遠行星的企圖
This marked the first manned attempt to reach this distant planet.
今天下午  世界今夜節目訪問了
This afternoon, The World Tonight recorded an interview...
遠離地球八千萬里  發現者號的機員
...with the crew at a distance of 80 million miles from Earth.
我們的話要傳到太空船  需要七分鐘的時間
It took 7 minutes for our words to reach the giant spacecraft...
不過這項時差已予以修正
...but this time delay has been edited from this recording.
記者馬丁艾默對機員們談話
Our reporter Martin Amer speaks to the crew.
發現者一號的機員包括五個人
The crew of Discovery One consists of five men...
和一套最新的H.A.L  9000型電腦系統
...and one of the latest generation of the HAL 9000 computers.
五人中有三人  是在太空船上睡覺
Three of the men were put aboard asleep...
說得更精確些  是保持在冬眠的狀態
...or to be more precise, in a state of hibernation:
他們就是查理亨特博士  杰克金波博士
Dr. Charles Hunter, Dr. Jack Kimball
以及維克多克明斯博士
and Dr. Victor Kaminsky.
下面就是我們和  任務指揮官大衛鮑曼博士
We spoke with mission commander, Dr. David Bowman...
和副指揮官  富蘭克普理博士的談話
...and his deputy, Dr. Frank Poole.
二位午安  一切都好嗎
Good afternoon, gentlemen. How is everything going?
太神奇了
Marvelous.
我們毫無怨尤
We have no complaints.
很高興聽到這句話  我想全世界的人
I'm glad to hear that. I'm sure the entire world...
都和我一樣祝福你們  有個平安成功的航行
...joins me in wishing you a safe, successful voyage.
-非常感謝  -謝謝你們
-Thanks very much. -Thank you.
雖然冬眠  在過去太空任務中曾使用過
Although hibernation has been used on previous space efforts...
但這是第一次在出發前
...this is the first time
將人員置于冬眠狀態
men were put into hibernation before departure.
為什么要這么做呢
Why was this done?
這樣做的目的  在使我們的生命支持能力
This was done to achieve the maximum conservation...
基本的食物與空氣  得到最大量的保存
...of our life-support capabilities, basically food and air.
現在冬眠的機員代表測量組
The three hibernating crew members represent the survey team.
他們的專長要等到我們  快接近木星時才會用到
Their efforts won't be utilized until we approach Jupiter.
普里博士  冬眠時究竟像什么樣子
Dr. Poole, what's it like while you're in hibernation?
完全像睡著般沒有知覺
It's exactly like being asleep. You have no sense of time.
唯一不同的是不會做夢
The only difference is that you don't dream.
據我所知  你一分鐘呼吸一次  真的嗎
As I understand it, you only breathe once a minute. Is this true?
那是真的  心跳一分鐘三次
Right, and the heart beats three times a minute.
體溫降至約攝氏三度
Body temperature is usually down to about three degrees centigrade.
發現者的第六位機員  并不擔心冬眠的問題
The sixth member of the crew was not concerned...
...about the problems of hibernation...
因為他是科技智慧最新結晶
...for he was the latest result in machine intelligence:
HAL系統  9000型電腦  它能夠復制...
The HAL 9000 computer, which can reproduce...
雖然有些專家  仍喜歡使用模擬一辭
...though some experts prefer to use the word "mimic"...
...大部份人腦的活動
...most of the activities of the human brain...
并具有無法計算的  較大速度與可靠性
...and with incalculably greater speed and reliability.
下面我們將與這部電腦談話
We next spoke with the HAL 9000 computer...
我們知道他有個名字叫赫爾
...whom, we learned, one addresses as "Hal. "
午安  赫爾  一切都好嗎
Hello, Hal. How's everything going?
午安  艾默先生  一切都非常順利
Good afternoon, Mr. Amer. Everything is going extremely well.
赫爾  在這次任務中  你有一大堆的責任
Hal, you have an enormous responsibility on this mission...
每個任務責任都很重要
...perhaps the greatest of any single mission element.
你是這艘太空船的首腦和中央神經系統
You're the brain and nervous system of the ship.
你的責任包括監視人們冬眠
Your responsibilities include watching over the men in hibernation.
對這樣的任務  你是否會缺乏信心
Does this ever cause you any lack of confidence?
艾默先生  讓我這樣說
Let me put it this way, Mr. Amer.
這套9000型系統的電腦是目前最可靠的電腦
The 9000 Series is the most reliable computer ever made.
9000型系統的電腦
No 9000 computer has ever made a mistake
從來沒有出現過錯誤  或是不實的資料
or distorted information.
我們使用實用的定義  極為簡單絕不可能產生錯誤
We are all, by any practical definition of the words...
...foolproof and incapable of error.
赫爾  不管你智慧多高  仍得依靠人們執行
Hal, despite your enormous intellect, are you ever frustrated...
你是否因此會產生挫折感
...by your dependence on people to carry out actions?
一點都不會
Not in the slightest bit.
我很高興和人們一起工作
I enjoy working with people.
我和普里博士  鮑曼博士  有著非常良好的關系
I have a stimulating relationship with Dr. Poole and Dr. Bowman.
我的任務范圍
My mission responsibilities
包括整個太空船的作業
range over the entire operation of the ship...
所以我非常忙碌
...so I am constantly occupied.
我把自己使用到最大程度
I am putting myself to the fullest possible use...
我想那是任何有責任感的人
...which is all, I think,
所希望做到的
that any conscious entity can ever hope to do.
普里博士  一年中大部份時間  都和赫爾一起生活
Dr. Poole, what's it like living for most of the year...
感覺如何
...in such close proximity with Hal?
是的  我和他非常的接近
It's like what you said earlier.
他正像是第六位機員
He's like a sixth member of the crew.
由于他會說話
You quickly get adjusted to the idea that he talks,
你會很快的調整你的觀念
and think of him...
當你對電腦講話時  會認為他真是另一個人
...really just as another person.
你會有一種感覺  那就是  他能夠作情緒上的反應
In talking to the computer, one gets the sense that he's capable...
...of emotional responses.
例如  當我問到他的能力時
When I asked him about his abilities...
我可以感受到他非常自負  自己精確完整的能力
...I sensed pride in his answer about his accuracy and perfection.
你相信赫爾真有感情嗎
Do you believe that Hal has genuine emotions?
是的  他表現得很有情感
Well, he acts like he has genuine emotions.
當然  他就是這樣設計  使我們更容易對他說話
He's programmed that way to make it easier for us to talk to him.
至于他是否真有情感
As to whether or not he has feelings...
我想是沒有人可以回答的
...is something I don't think anyone can truthfully answer.
對不起  富蘭克
Excuse me, Frank.
什么事赫爾
What is it, Hal?
我剛接到你父母的電訊
We've got the transmission from your parents coming in.
好的
Fine.
請接過來  把我移過去一點  好嗎
Put it on here, please. Take me in a bit.
當然可以
Certainly.
哈羅  富蘭克  親愛的  祝你生日快樂
Happy birthday, darling!
祝你生日快樂  萬事如意
Happy birthday. Many happy returns.
請稍為高一點
A bit higher, Hal.
我和你媽媽都感覺很好
Mother and I are both feeling wonderful.
瑞和莎莉本來也要來此
Ray and Sally were going to be here...
但是瑞的背痛又發作了
...but Ray's back went bad on him again.
你喜歡這個生日蛋糕嗎
How do you like your cake, dear?
看起來很不錯  是不是
It's great, doesn't it?
可惜你不能與我們共享
Sorry you can't join us.
對了  前幾天碰到鮑伯
I ran into Bob the other day.
他要我代他祝你生日快樂
He said to wish you happy birthday.
我所有的學生也虔誠祝福你
All my students send their best wishes too.
你知道他們整天都在談論你
They talk about you all the time.
你是二年級的大名人
You're a big celebrity in the second grade.
你知道嗎  上星期我們還上電視呢
We were on TV last week.
你母親和我  還有大衛父母都接受訪問
Your mom and I and Dave's parents were asked...
問我們對于杰出兒子的感受
...what we thought of our illustrious son.
你可以想像得到
Imagine what we told them.
我們告訴他們什么嗎我想可能在下星期四播出
It's being broadcast next Thursday.
也許你可以收到
Perhaps you can listen in.
關于艾拉蓮和比爾的消息  我們也感到激動  親愛的
We're thrilled about Elaine and Bill.
我很高興買禮物送你  但請告訴我可以花多少錢
I'll be glad to get the gift, but tell me how much to spend.
對了  富蘭克  關于你的薪水
Oh, Frank, about your AGS- 19 payments...
我想我幫你處理好了
...I think I straightened it out.
昨天我和會計室的人談過
I talked to the accounting office yesterday...
你下個月就可領到較高薪水
...and they said you'd be receiving your higher rates of pay by next month.
我想不出還有什么要說
I can't think of anything else to say.
-代我們向大衛問好  -記得代我們向他致意
-Give our love to Dave. -Be sure to give him our best regards.
祝你有個最愉快的生日
We wish you the very happiest of birthdays.
生日快樂
All the best, son.
祝你生日快樂
Happy birthday to you.
祝親愛的富蘭克生日快樂
Happy birthday, dear Frank
祝你生日快樂
Happy birthday to you.
下星期三再見
See you next Wednesday.
富蘭克  生日快樂
Happy birthday, Frank.
謝謝你赫爾  請將椅子調低
Thank you, Hal. A bit flatter, please.
皇后吃卒
Anyway, queen takes pawn.
主教吃騎士的卒
Bishop takes knight's pawn.
這步如何
Lousy move.
好  城堡進一步到國王
Rook to king one.
富蘭克  抱歉我想你輸了
I'm sorry, Frank. I think you missed it.
女王進三到主教  主教吃女王  騎士吃主教
Queen to bishop three. Bishop takes queen.
將軍
Knight takes bishop. Mate.
看起來好像你對
Looks like you're right. I resign.
謝謝你  這盤棋下得很愉快
Thank you for a very enjoyable game.
彼此彼此
Thank you.
-大衛  晚安  -赫爾  一切都好嗎
-Good evening. -How are you, Hal?
-一切都好  你呢  -還不錯
-Everything's running smoothly. You? -Not too bad.
-你有沒有做些別的事  -只畫了幾張素描
-Have you been doing more work? -A few sketches.
-可以讓我看看嗎  -當然可以
-May I see them? -Sure.
大衛  你畫得很不錯
That's a very nice rendering, Dave.
我認為你有很大進步
I think you've improved a great deal.
-請你再拿近一點好嗎  -當然可以
-Can you hold it a bit closer? -Sure.
那不是亨利博士嗎  是的
That's Dr. Hunter, isn't it?
問你一個私人問題  不介意吧
By the way...
...do you mind if I ask you a personal question?
一點也不介意
No, not at all.
請原諒我的好奇  但在過去的幾星期中
Well, forgive me for being so inquisitive...
我懷疑你們對這次任務  是否另有想法
...but lately I've wondered...
...whether you might be having second thoughts about the mission?
這是什么意思
How do you mean?
這很難解釋
Well, it's rather difficult to define.
也許只是我對此事的關心
Perhaps I'm just projecting my own concern about it.
你知道對于和這次任務  有關的一切怪事
I know I've never completely freed myself of the suspicion...
我的疑心從未完全解除
...that there are some extremely odd things about this mission.
我想你多少同意我的看法
I'm sure you'll agree there's some truth in what I say.
我不知道  那是個相當難以回答的問題
That's a rather difficult question to answer.
大衛  討論這件事你不介意嗎
You don't mind talking about it, do you, Dave?
不  一點都不介意
No, not at all.
相信大家在出發前都聽過  在我們四周流傳的一些謠言
Certainly no one could have been unaware of the very...
...strange stories floating around before we left.
有關于月球上  有某樣東西被挖掘出來的謠言
Rumors about something being dug up on the moon.
我從不相信這些謠言
I never gave these stories much credence...
但就某些已發生的事來說
...but particularly in view of some other things that have happened...
我發現很難把他們忘掉
...I find them difficult to put out of my mind.
例如說
For instance...
我們的裝備是如此安全周密
...the way all our preparations were kept under such tight security.
亨利博士  金波博士  和克明斯基博士
And the melodramatic touch of putting Drs. Hunter...
在各別訓練四個月后
...Kimball, and Kaminsky aboard...
以非常戲劇性的手法
...already in hibernation,
在冬眠狀態下登上太空船
after four months of training on their own.
你是為了心理報告而問的
You working up your crew psychology report?
當然是的
Of course I am.
很抱歉問你這件事  我知道有點可笑
Sorry about this. I know it's a bit silly.
等等
Just a moment.
我剛在AE35單位中  找到一項故障
I've just picked up a fault in the AE-35 unit.
在72小時內它將完全失效
It's going to go 100 percent failure within 72 hours.
-到現在為止  仍在你的作業極限內嗎  -是的
-Is it still within operational limits? -Yes.
它會保持現狀直到完全失效
And it will stay that way until it fails.
我們還有72小時可以修護
We have 72 hours till failure?
是的  這個數字完全可靠
Yes. That's a completely reliable figure.
看樣子我們必須把它拿進來  不過我得先和富蘭克商量
Then we'll bring it in. I'll go over it with Frank...
然后再與任務控制中心聯絡  請復印一份資料給我
...and get on to Mission Control. Let me have the hard copy on it.
X光一號  這是任務中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
你的2013訊息收到了
Roger your two-zero-one-three.
抱歉  伙伴們  目前有點小麻煩
Sorry you fellows are having a bit of trouble.
我們正在觀察
We're reviewing telemetric information
任務模擬器上的電傳資料
in our simulator and will advise.
羅杰  你準備前往EVA
Roger your plan to go EVA
在AE35失效前加以更換
and replace alpha-echo-3-5 unit...
羅杰  你準備去EVA  在AE35失效前加以更換
...prior to failure.
請準備輔助艙前往EVA
Prepare B-pod for EVA, Hal.
請打開艙門  赫爾
Open the pod doors, Hal.
赫爾  真該死  就是找不到一點毛病
I'm damned if I can find anything wrong with it.
是啊
Yes...
真是令人費解
...it's puzzling.
我以前從來沒見過這樣的事
I don't think I've ever seen anything quite like this before.
我建議我們把它放回去
I would recommend...
繼續運作到失效為止
...that we put the unit back in operation and let it fail.
這樣可很簡單的追查出原因
It should then be a simple matter to track down the cause.
我們可以承受暫時停止通信  以便更換它
We can certainly afford to be out of communication...
...for the short time it will take to replace it.
X光一號  這是控制中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
你的1930訊息收到了
Roger your one-niner-three-zero.
我們同意你的計劃  更換一號單位以檢查錯誤
We concur with your plan to replace unit to check fault prediction.
同時必須告訴你們  我們初步調查發現
We advise you that our preliminary findings...
你們船上的三倍九零電腦  失效預測功能有問題
...indicate that your onboard 9000 computer...
...is in error predicting the fault.
重覆一次  失效預測功能有問題
I say again, in error predicting the fault.
我知道這聽起來不太可能
I know this sounds rather incredible,
不過這個結論是根據...
but this conclusion is based on...
三倍九零電腦計算出來的
...the results from our twin 9000 computer.
我們自己也感到懷疑  我們正在做橫向的例行檢查
We're skeptical, and we're running cross-checking routines...
...to determine reliability of this conclusion.
對這個故障感到抱歉  各位
Sorry about this little snag.
只要我們一查出結果  便會馬上通知你們
We'll get this info to you as soon as we work it out.
X光一號  這是任務中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
2091訊息傳送完畢
Two-zero-four-nine. Transmission concluded.
我希望你們兩人  對這件事不要操心
I hope the two of you are not concerned about this.
不  我并不操心
No, I'm not, Hal.
真的嗎
Are you quite sure?
-真的  不過我倒想問你一個問題  -當然可以
-Yeah. I'd like to ask you a question. -Of course.
你認為你和成套9000  電腦間有何矛冒
How do you account for the discrepancy between you and the twin 9000?
我不認為有什么問題
Well, I don't think there is any question about it.
這只能歸咎于人為的錯誤
It can only be attributable to human error.
這類錯誤以前也發生過
This sort of thing has cropped up before...
而且總是由于人為的疏忽
...and it has always been due to human error.
聽我說  赫爾
Listen, Hal...
9000型電腦  從來沒有出錯的例子嗎
...there's never been any instance at all...
...of a computer error occurring in a 9000 Series, has there?
從沒有  富蘭克
None whatsoever, Frank.
9000型電腦有完美的記錄
The 9000 Series has a perfect operational record.
當然  我知道  9000型電腦的偉大成就
I know the wonderful achievements of the 9000 Series, but....
但你確定即使最小的錯誤
Are you certain there's never been
都不曾發生過嗎
even the most insignificant computer error?
富蘭克  從沒有
None whatsoever, Frank.
老實說  對這件事我自己并不擔心
Quite honestly, I wouldn't worry myself about that.
好了  赫爾  我的確相信
Well, I'm sure you're right, Hal.
你是對的  非常謝謝你
Fine. Thanks very much.
法蘭克  C艙的送話器有點小毛病
I'm having trouble with my transmitter in C-pod.
你能不能和我一同檢查
Would you come down and take a look at it with me?
赫爾  回頭見
See you later, Hal.
赫爾  請轉動C艙
Rotate C-pod, please, Hal.
大衛  你發現什么毛病
What sort of trouble are you having?
我在D頻道中收到一些干擾
I've been getting some interference in D-channel.
我們去看看
We'll have a look at it.
赫爾  請開門
Open the door, Hal.
請轉動備用艙  赫爾
Rotate pod, please, Hal.
停住備用艙
Stop pod rotation, please, Hal.
請轉動備用艙  赫爾
Rotate the pod, please, Hal.
我想他聽不到我們的談話
I don't think he can hear us.
請轉動備用艙  赫爾
Rotate the pod, please, Hal!
是的  的確沒問題了
Yeah, I'm sure we're okay.
你認為如何
What do you think?
-我不確定  你呢  -我覺得它不太對勁
-I'm not sure. What do you think? -I've got a bad feeling about him.
-是嗎  -是的
-You do? -Yeah. Definitely.
你說不是嗎
Don't you?
我不知道  我想是的
I don't know. I think so.
你知道他說得沒錯
He's right about the 9000 Series
9000型電腦有完美的記錄
having a perfect operational record.
確實
They do.
那聽起來似乎有點  像著名的末世之言
Unfortunately, that sounds a little like famous last words.
但他不正是以這種觀念  對失效作方式上的分析
Still, it was his idea to carry out the failure mode analysis.
他的確顯示出  他的誠實與自信
It certainly indicates his integrity and self-confidence.
假如他是錯的話  這倒是最好的證明方法
If he were wrong that would prove it.
假如他知道他是錯的話
It would be if he knew he was wrong.
我是搞不清楚  但我感到有些奇怪
I can't put my finger on it, but I sense something strange about him.
沒有不把一號單位  放回去的更好理由
There's no reason not to put back the unit and...
-繼續失效上的分析  -我同意
-...carry on with the failure analysis. -No, no, I agree about that.
好的  那就試看看
Let's get on with it.
好吧  但是大衛
Okay. But, look, Dave.
如果  我們把這個機件放回去  它并未失效
Say we put the unit back and it doesn't fail?
赫爾豈不是很沒面子
That would pretty well wrap it up as far as Hal is concerned.
-那我將會有  -非常嚴重的麻煩不是嗎
-We'd be in very serious trouble. -We would, wouldn't we?
我們能做什么呢
What the hell can we do?
我們不可能有太多選擇
We wouldn't have too many alternatives.
我不認為我們有任何選擇
We wouldn't have any alternatives.
在這船上沒有那一部份  不是在他控制下
Every aspect of ship operations is under his control.
If he's malfunctioning...
除了關機  我想不出別的方法
...I don't see any choice but disconnection.
我同意你的看法
I'm afraid I agree with you.
也沒有其他的看法
There'd be nothing else to do.
這真有點捉弄人  是的
It'd be a bit tricky.
我們必須切斷它的主腦功能
We'd have to cut his higher brain functions...
而不干擾自動調節系統
...without disturbing the purely automatic and regulatory systems.
同時必須在地面電腦控制下  維持傳送程序以繼續任務
We'd have to work out the details...
...of continuing under ground-based computer control.
是的  看來這種方法  比讓赫爾繼續控制安全多了
Yeah. That's far safer than allowing Hal to continue to run things.
我剛想到另一件事
Another thing just occurred to me.
九千型電腦從沒有被關機過
No 9000 computer has ever been disconnected.
是啊  九千型電腦  過去也沒有失誤過
No 9000 computer has ever fouled up.
那倒不是我的意思
That's not what I mean.
我不知道  他對此事的想法如何
I'm not so sure what he'd think about it.
中斷
赫爾  請開輔助艙通道門
Prepare G-pod for EVA, Hal.
無線電聯絡上他了嗎
Any contact with him yet?
不行  還是無法聯絡
The radio is still dead.
-你檢查過了嗎  -我檢查過了
-Do you have a positive track on him? -I have a good track.
你知道發生什么事  赫爾
Do you know what happened?
大衛  抱歉  我的資訊不足
I'm sorry, Dave. I don't have enough information.
赫爾  請開輔助艙通道門
Open the pod door, Hal.
電腦失效
生命功能情況危急
生命功能結束
赫爾  請開輔助艙通道門
Open the pod bay doors, please, Hal.
赫爾  你聽得見我說話嗎
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
Do you read me, Hal?
赫爾  你聽得見嗎
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
聽得見嗎  赫爾
Do you read me, Hal?
我聽得見  大衛  我聽得見你說話
Affirmative, Dave. I read you.
請開輔助艙通道門
Open the pod bay doors, Hal.
我恐怕不能這樣做
I'm sorry, Dave. I'm afraid I can't do that.
有什么問題嗎
What's the problem?
我想你知道問題所在  就像我現在所做一樣
I think you know what the problem is just as well as I do.
赫爾  你在說什么
What are you talking about, Hal?
這次任務對我太重要了  不能讓你破壞
This mission is too important for me to allow you to jeopardize it.
我不懂你在說什么  赫爾
I don't know what you're talking about, Hal.
我知道你們計劃將我關機
I know that you and Frank were planning to disconnect me...
那是我不允許發生的事
...and that's something I cannot allow to happen.
赫爾  你怎會有這種  該死的想法
Where did you get that idea, Hal?
大衛  雖然你采取了  非常徹底的防范
Although you took very thorough precautions in the pod...
讓我聽不見
...against my hearing you...
但是我會讀唇語
...I could see your lips move.
好的  赫爾
All right, Hal.
我從緊急阻隔門進去
I'll go in through the emergency air lock.
大衛  沒有太空盔
Without your space helmet, Dave...
你會發現那是相當困難
...you're going to find that rather difficult.
我不想再和你辯論  赫爾
Hal, I won't argue with you anymore.
請開門吧
Open the doors!
大衛
Dave...
這段談話  不能達到任何目的  再見
...this conversation can serve no purpose anymore. Goodbye.
赫爾
Hal?
你以為你在做什么  大衛
Just what do you think you're doing, Dave?
大衛
Dave...
我認為我該給你一個答案
...I really think I'm entitled to an answer to that question.
我知道我最近不太對勁
I know everything hasn't been quite right with me...
但我可以很有信心的保證
...but I can assure you now...
...very confidently...
將會再度好起來
...that it's going to be all right again.
我現在覺得好多了
I feel much better now.
我真的覺得好多了
I really do.
聽我說  大衛
Look, Dave...
我可以了解你的憤怒
...I can see you're really upset about this.
我認為你應冷靜的坐下來
I honestly think you ought to sit down calmly...
吃片鎮靜劑  好好的想想看
...take a stress pill and think things over.
我知道  最近我曾經  作了一些很差勁的決定
I know I've made some very poor decisions recently...
但我可以完全向你保證
...but I can give you my complete assurance...
我的工作將回復正常
...that my work will be back to normal.
對這次任務
I've still got the greatest enthusiasm
我們具有最大的信心和熱忱
and confidence in the mission...
同時我很想要幫助你
...and I want to help you.
大衛
Dave...
停手
...stop.
停下來  行么
Stop, will you?
停下來  大衛
Stop, Dave.
請你停止好嗎大衛
Will you stop, Dave?
大衛  停手
Stop, Dave.
我害怕
I'm afraid.
大衛  我害怕
I'm afraid, Dave.
我的智力正在消失
My mind is going.
我可以感覺到
I can feel it.
我的智力正在消失
My mind is going.
這是毫無疑問的
There is no question about it.
我可以感覺到
I can feel it.
我害怕
I'm...
...afraid.
午安
Good afternoon...
各位先生
...gentlemen.
我是赫爾  九千型電腦
I am a HAL 9000 computer.
我開始操作是在伊利諾州
I became operational...
...at the HAL plant...
威爾巴拉的HAL工廠
...in Urbana, Illinois...
時間是1992年1月12日
...on the 12th of January, 1992.
我的老師是藍利先生
My instructor was Mr. Langley...
他教我唱過一首歌
...and he taught me to sing a song.
如果你喜歡聽
If you'd like to hear it...
我可以為你唱
...I can sing it for you.
是的  赫爾  我喜歡聽
Yes, I'd like to hear it, Hal.
你就為我唱吧
Sing it for me.
歌名叫黛西
It's called "Daisy. "
各位先生  午安
Good day, gentlemen.
這是一卷預錄的簡報資料
This is a prerecorded briefing...
在你們出發前制作的
...made prior to your departure...
為了高度重要的保密理由
...and which, for security reasons of the highest importance...
在任務中  只有太空船上的
...has been known on board
九千型電腦知道事情真相
during the mission...
在任務中  只有太空船上的
...only by your
九千型電腦知道事情真相
HAL 9000 computer.
你們現在是在木星的太空中
Now that you are in Jupiter's space...
全部船員均已蘇醒
...and the entire crew is revived...
現在真相可以公布了
...it can be told to you.
十八個月前在地球以外
Eighteen months ago...
發現了第一個  有生命才智的證據
...the first evidence of intelligent life off the Earth...
...was discovered.
被埋藏在月球表面四十尺下
It was buried 40 feet below the lunar surface...
靠近克拉科火山口
...near the crater Tycho.
除了一個非常強有力的
Except for a single, very powerful...
放射性發光體對準木星外
...radio emission aimed at Jupiter...
這四百萬年高齡的黑巖石  仍舊保持完全無生命狀態
...the 4-million-year-old monolith has remained completely inert...
它的根源與目的
...its origin and purpose...
至今仍是一個謎
...still a total mystery.
木星以及無限穹蒼
謝謝觀賞